And I really want electric guitar like
little moments between here. Okay, let's
just like sing that in and see if we can
get them [music]
>> falling in pieces.
Let's go back to the start.
>> Yeah.
What's up? I'm Henry. I'm on the product
team of Sunno Studio and I'm going to be
showing you all Studio 2.0. We're stoked
about this. We're going to start with a
blank canvas, cook up some tunes, and I
see where it takes us and I'm going to
explain everything along the way. Okay,
when you first get to Studio, you're
going to see this blank canvas. At the
top, we have our buttons for controlling
playback. This is play and pause. This
controls the metronome. So, that
clicking sound you hear will help you
keep time. And then on the left hand
side, we can see two tracks. Here we
have an audio track. We have a MIDI
track which is brand new to studio. And
if I want to create more of these at any
time, I click the add new track and it
gives me these choices. I love keyboard
shortcuts, so I use shift T to pull open
that menu and then follow up with A or
follow up with M to create these various
tracks. I can double click on the track
header to toggle open this panel at the
bottom. So, this panel is going to have
my instrument and then a bunch of audio
effects. You can see that right now I've
got a wavetable synth open here. But
we're going to be adding different
instrument types over time. And I have a
patch loaded up in this wavetable synth
that sounds like this.
[music]
So, how am I playing that? Well, I'm
actually using my laptop keyboard to
type in those notes. So, if you press
command K or you press this little
keyboard button in the bottom right,
you'll pull up this handy little
reference guide that shows you which
keys on your keyboard correspond to
which notes on this little virtual
keyboard. So,
it takes some practice, but you can
learn to play melodies and chords on
your computer keyboard. You can also, of
course, plug in a MIDI keyboard and play
in that way, but sometimes you're on the
go, you're in an airport, you're on a
train, and you want to just be able to
type in and write with your laptop
keyboard. Let's record into the project.
This is our tempo up here. So, we can
drag it up or down to change
the speed.
I'm going to go to 133, which is a tempo
that I love. Upbeat. Okay. So, now let's
record something in. And this little red
illuminated button will tell us which
track is listening for a recording. So
in this case, we want to be listening
for the MIDI track. So I'm going to arm
the track by clicking this red button.
Um, so this part that I'm envisioning is
going to start as like a kind of a just
a simple drone and then I'm going to add
a second track and add some bass.
[music]
Okay, here we go.
>> [music]
>> Don't lost.
[music]
Cool. So, that is our part. Um, and I'm
kind of picturing that like the song
kind of starts here and this could be a
little intro perhaps. So, I'll command E
to split this. Maybe I'll drag it over
here. Um, so bar two is kind of the
start of our song for me. Um,
oh no, bar three. I'm actually going to
duplicate this.
And let's record in a bass part. So now
I'm going to record on this one. I can
press Z and X to change the octave. So
that will be our this will be our bass.
So let's uh let's record this.
[music]
>> [music]
>> Awesome. And I want to copy this out a
little bit. And keep in mind that if you
drag the MIDI notes before the beginning
of the clip, then they'll get cut off.
So you want to make sure they're always
in bounds. And I'm gonna go ahead and
select these notes and press the
quantize button to make sure they're
nice and locked onto the grid. And same
thing with these ones.
Quantize the quarter notes. And I'm
pressing at two to open and close the
piano roll down here. But you can also
do it by double clicking on the actual
clip itself. Okay. So now we have our
MIDI parts.
>> [music]
>> I think I wanted this to be like a
little bit more like filtered and washed
out. So, let's go ahead and add an audio
effect. So, once again, double click on
this to open here. And we're going to
add an EQ, which is going to allow me to
change the frequency spectrum here.
And I'm going to go ahead and cut off
the high frequencies.
[music]
>> [music]
>> And I'm going to add a reverb to this as
well.
[music]
Okay. So, now let's go ahead and add
something else here. So, I'm going to
press enter, which is going to open up
this new chat panel. This is where a lot
of your interaction is going to happen
in Studio 2.0. This chat enables you to
create new audio onto the timeline,
create MIDI, you can even create new
plugins. I'm going to use it right now
to add a synth part. And you can even
see that it's suggesting it right here.
Um, add an ambient synth stem
drone. I want it to be like lush
sounding. And I just wanted to accompany
what's already on the timeline here.
Okay. So, let's listen back to the synth
part. [music]
>> [music]
>> Okay, that's that's kind of what I was
hoping for. Um, I can use the up and
down arrows or press this to hear the
other option, too. So, let's listen to
this one.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Okay. I love both of those. Um, this one
the timing got a little messed up in the
middle. So, I'm going to go ahead and
just like copy this. I'm going to commit
the first one, but I'm going to paste
the second one down here just so we have
it. And I'm going to just shift it
around a little bit because that is
where it felt like it was right. Let's
solo these. And let's just see what
happens if I have both playing at the
same time. Um, maybe it'll be kind of
nice. [music]
Oh, and I've just gone ahead and used
this little pan control to put this in
our left ear and this one in my right
ear.
>> [music]
>> Wolf.
[music]
>> [music]
>> Cool. Okay, I like this. Uh, let's
record some
vocals. Um, and I'm just going to keep
playing the laptop speakers out loud
because I've got a mic that's pretty
close and directional. Oh, and before I
record, we should calibrate the
microphone. This is a new thing with
Studio 2 where I can come here, say
calibrate, and if I point the mic at the
speakers, it's going to make some clicks
and record how long it takes for those
clicks to travel all the way back
through the audio system. And this will
help us calibrate and make sure that the
audio lands on the timeline exactly
where it should.
Okay, 55 milliseconds. So now let us
record.
It [music] must have been a bad moment.
Getting late and still working
and me ignoring [singing] all the
warnings cautionary stories over my
head.
You must have had a bad feeling. [music]
Saw the cracks in the ceiling.
And me pretending I don't see you.
>> Now we do the painful thing and we
listen back to it. It must [music] have
been a bad morning
getting late and still working
and me ignoring [music] all the
warnings. Cautionary stories over my
head.
You must have had a bad feeling. [music]
Saw the cracks in the ceiling
and me pretending I don't see. We're
just [music] in a season painted red.
Yeah. and I'm falling apart. We're
getting somewhere. Um, I think what I
want to do now is play some basic guitar
onto this, but then I'm going to have
Sunno make that guitar a little bit
better. Um, so let's give this a try.
And right now we're just stacking the
layers. But, um, let's do this. So,
shift T A to make a new audio track.
We're going to change the input to this.
We're going to arm that. We're going to
point the mic at the guitar.
Haphazardly, I might add.
[music]
working
cautionary stories over my head.
You must have had a bad feeling. [music]
Saw the cracks in the
pretend. [music]
[music]
>> Great. Okay,
that'll do as far as guitar goes. Let's
go ahead
and turn these guitars into something.
[music]
>> [music]
>> Um, cool. So, you can hear there I got a
little bit ahead of the beat. So, I
could double click on this to open up
the audio like inspector here. And I
could drop like in moments where the
audio has gotten ahead of the beat. I
can lock these in place over here. And I
can, you know, just nudge these into the
right spot.
Okay, great. So, we'll return back to
these guitars. So, first thing I'm going
to do is right now all of these tracks
have bad names. So, I'm going to press
enter and say, can you rename all my
track
names to make sense? And while it thinks
about that, a big part of recording
audio into a digital audio workstation
is to be able to modify the sound a
little bit after the fact. So, I can
either add the effects manually by
clicking add effect and picking from
this list, or I could once again just
talk to the chat. So, we can see that it
just finished renaming all this stuff.
Um, these are pretty good titles that it
picked. And let's go ahead and say, can
you add a chain of vocal effects here?
And it's going to go ahead and think
about which effects would be good to add
to this track. Um, it's probably going
to dial in some parameters for us, which
I'm going to then tweak later. Cool. So,
it's gone ahead and added an EQ,
compressor, reverb, and delay, which are
pretty good choices. So, let's start by
turning these off. So, we're going to
start with the EQ.
[music]
>> So, I want
take out a few of these lows and low cut
a little bit
[music] late and still
me ignoring all the warnings.
Yeah, I like it brighter.
>> Cool. And there's a little bit of
background noise, too. So, I'm actually
gonna go ahead and add a noise gate,
which is here. Cool. Let's fly it over
here.
>> I could dial these in a little bit.
Let's just give ourselves a little bit
of a a little bit of gentleness there.
Okay. And then compressor time.
>> And my gain is too high. Must have been
a bad moment.
Getting late and still working
and me ignoring all the warnings.
Cautionary stories over my head.
>> And if you're wondering what I'm doing
here twiddling these knobs, uh we've got
some other videos about these effects
that dive deeper into what they are and
how to use them. Okay, reverb time. Must
have been a [singing] bad moment.
Getting late and still working
and me ignoring [singing] all the
>> cool and then a delay.
[singing]
>> Getting late and still
ignoring all the warnings
over.
>> Okay, there's some pitch issues here
too. We don't have any sort of tuning
plugin in here quite yet, but someday I
expect that will come. Um, cool. So, our
vocal sounding a little bit more like a
real vocal.
[music]
[music and singing]
>> Cautionary stories over my head.
Must have had a bad [music] feeling.
Saw the cracks in the ceiling.
Let's turn this delay down a little bit.
Okay. So, one of the things that I love
to do is take an idea that I have and
then use Sunno's cover feature and
create an entirely new song based on
that little snippet. And then we can go
back in. We can pull little stems and
things out of here. So, um, let's just
record in the next section here with
just vocal and guitar. And I'll just do
it together. So, audio track. I'm going
to go ahead and plug my headphones back
in. Let's do it.
And I'm falling apart. [music]
And I'm falling to pieces.
Let's [snorts] go back to the start.
Baby, give me a reason
[music] to stay. to stay.
[music]
Cool. Okay. So, now we've like now we've
done something funky. We've got like our
track and this first bit that has all
this [music]
>> Yeah. It has those since
>> and then we've got our little second
like you know like straight in there.
[music]
>> Let's go back to the start. [music]
Baby give me a reason
to [music] stay. To stay.
Okay. So between these two things, we've
like articulated kind of what this song
should be like. In the first half, we've
got like the ambient synths, we've got
some guitar parts, there's like a little
bit more on the production, and then for
this pre chorus, we've got just like a
total scratch recording. We can just
squash these things together. So I'm
going to go select this whole region,
and I'm going to say export full sum. So
what this is going to do is it's going
to save bad moment to my uh library. So,
I can go here and, you know, we've got
the we've got the song. And so, I'm
going to come here and say remix. I'm
going to cover it. Um, and now we've
like totally shifted to a different
interface. We're soon going to make it
easier to do this process within Studio
2, but you got to bear with us as we
develop these products. Um, okay. And
it's it's already made an attempt to
describe the styles here. Indie rock. I
actually don't want it to be indie rock.
I want it to be more like indie folk.
Great. All these things are good. Yeah,
this is this should be good. Let's let's
see what happens. And the goal is to
find something that has just like an
element or two that we can pull out and
play with.
[music]
>> Yeah.
>> Getting late and still working.
[music]
>> Yeah.
Yeah. So, this is this [music] one's
going to be good. So, let's like this
one. I'm going to pop back into my
studio project here. And I'm going to
pull up my library and make sure that
I'm in the same workspace we were just
working in. Bad moment too. And I can
filter by like songs. So, this is the
one we just did. Let's pull this onto
the timeline. And it'll automatically be
tempo adjusted to fit the grid here.
[music]
>> So, let's go ahead and fly this over to
where our vocal does that. It must have
been a bad It must have
>> It must have
It must have been a bad [music]
>> Okay, I don't quite have it like this
indie folk singer does, but what we're
going to do is we're going to pull out
some of these stems. So, I'm going to
rightclick. I'm going to say get stems.
I'm going to choose the advanced mode.
And what I really want out of this is
guitar. I want bass. I want lead vocal.
I want I mean what's what else is in
here?
>> Oh yeah, drums.
[music]
And
>> I actually just want all the guitars.
>> [music]
>> Is that like [music] a little piano in
the back there?
Yeah. Cool.
Okay. So, now we're pulling all of these
individual elements out of the cover and
we're going to go ahead and combine them
with the existing things that we already
dragged onto the timeline and we're
going to kind of smush them together and
make like a little composite of the two.
Okay. Okay, so now that these stems have
generated, I'm going to click insert all
and it's going to arrange them with the
same timing as the original track here.
So let's listen.
[music]
[singing]
>> The pitchiness of this is going to kill
me. Okay, let's let's layer me with this
indie girl because I think that is going
to sound nice.
moment
getting late and still [music] working
[singing]
ignoring all the warnings. Cautionary
stories [music] over my head. But yeah,
I'm also just going to record some more
later. I think I I can do better than
that. But um Okay, we had this cool
piano out here. Let's listen to this.
Yeah, not my favorite stem, actually.
There we go.
That'll be nice. And let's listen to
[music]
Okay, we'll have the synth moments,
right? We'll they'll kind of swell in
and then we'll cut them. We'll go to
that drag guitar and then we'll bring in
the synths quietly when we get to the
second little verse here.
It must have been a bad moment
getting late and still working
[music and singing]
and me ignoring all the warnings and
cautionary. [music]
>> We're going to go listen to this vocal.
>> You [music] must have a bad feeling.
Saw the cracks in the ceiling [music]
and we pretend [singing]
we're just in a season painted red.
[music]
And I'm falling apart.
And I'm falling in pieces. [music]
Let's go back to the start.
Baby, [music and singing] give me a
reason. Let's go back to the start.
Let's go back to the start.
Baby, [music and singing] give me a
reason
to say to say.
Yeah. And I'm falling [music] apart.
>> Oh yeah. Let's get that out of here.
>> And I'm falling in pieces.
Let's go back to the start. [music]
Baby, give me a reason
to stay. [music]
[music]
Okay, we need some more stuff here. So,
let's um
Okay, let's see if we can get this to
double that um that electric guitar
line. So, let's say add another electric
guitar part here like uh crunchy
through a big
amp stack. So, now this is going to cook
up a brand new track that's going to
accompany that chorus moment.
[music]
>> [music]
>> Wow, that's wild.
So, that's really where this should
start.
[music]
Yeah, I think there's a little part in
there that we can use.
Cool. And then we will cut that off and
fade it out there.
>> [music]
>> Stay. Stay.
I want some keys in here, too. So, let's
see what happens if we Oh, I should
actually What I should do is play the
keys in here. I'm pulling in the big
guns for this one. Okay, we got our MIDI
keyboard set up. Let's uh let's play
this part in.
Stay.
[music]
Okay, messing things up. But we can
always just edit the MIDI after the
fact.
[music]
>> [music]
>> Battle.
Cool. And that will do just fine for us.
>> [music]
[snorts]
[music]
>> Great. Okay, we got this MIDI where we
want it.
[music]
Cool. So, I'm going to go select this
region and say uh cover this onto a new
audio track as
uh keyboard.
[music]
>> [music]
>> Whoa. Okay, that was really nice. That's
what I I might as well listen to the
other version, I guess. But
[music]
this one's nice.
[music] I'm going to mute the MIDI.
>> [music]
>> And that's kind of a nice little outro.
Okay, let's just do one little detail
thing. I'm going to take this tiny
little snare noise and I'm going to make
a whole new audio track just for the
snare noise. I'm going to open this up
and I'm going to say reverse. So, it's
going to kind of give us like a into the
outro. [music]
Little detail. I'm liking how this is
coming together. Uh, let's go back in
and I can I just have to record another
vocal take or two and see if we can make
this better. and check.
>> Must have been a bad
must have been a bad moment.
Getting late and still
ignoring [singing] all the warnings
over my head.
>> Cool. Okay, let's do another one really
fast while this one processes
and I'm falling apart.
>> [music]
>> Yeah, I'm falling to pieces.
Let's go back to the start.
[music] Oh, baby, give me a reason
to stay. To stay.
[music]
Sweet. I think I like that one the best.
I'm guessing this becomes the the lead.
[snorts] So, let's uh go ahead and pan
these left and right over here.
It must have been a badoment.
>> Oh, we need the audio effects and
everything, too. So, to do that quickly,
I'm just going to duplicate this track
and bring in the audio here. Duplicate
it again. Bring in the audio here. And
so, what we've just done is by
duplicating the track, now all of those
effects are going to duplicate as well.
Must have been a badoment.
>> Oh, that moment pitchiness is still
bothering me.
[singing]
>> Who's doing that? Who's doing that?
>> Better. [snorts] I'm just going to I'm
just going to cut you out with a fade.
He's still working [music and singing]
in me ignoring all the warnings,
cautionary [music] stories [singing]
over my head.
You must have had a bad feels
[music] in the ceiling
and me pretending I don't see. We're
just in a season.
>> We got to turn these way down.
All the cracks in the ceiling [music]
and me pretending I don't see. We're
just in a season [music] painted red.
Falling aart.
>> I actually really like that female
vocal. I think if I was going to like
finish up the song, I might bring in
someone else to track it. I might uh
figure out like more of a duet structure
with like another verse. But for now,
let's just fly that part in and see how
it all sounds. So that was here
[music and singing]
>> and I'm falling apart
and I'm falling to pieces.
Let's go back to the start. [music]
Baby, give me a [singing] reason.
And I'm a little bit ahead of the beat
on these. So I'm just gonna like nudge
the whole thing
>> and I'm falling to pieces. [music]
Let's go back to the start.
Baby [music and singing]
[music]
>> and I really want electric guitar like
little moments between here.
>> [music]
[singing]
>> Okay, let's just like sing that in and
see if we can get them like the right
input again. We'll have to make this
automatic at some point
[music and singing]
>> and I'm falling
[music]
down.
>> Let's go back to the start.
So, let's try this. Um, so make this a
lead electric guitar solo. Tasty.
We'll see what happens. Okay.
[music]
Okay. And then we're not gonna need this
part, but let's hear that.
>> And then I really just want to cut that
piece.
Let's go back to the start. [music]
>> Yeah.
>> Okay.
[music]
[singing]
>> And we'll just paste that over.
Baby
to stay to stay [music]
to stay to stay.
>> And that's where that little big moment
was supposed to go.
[music]
>> Cool. We'll just leave it there. But
that is really tasty and nice. and
[music] I'm falling apart
and I'm falling pieces.
>> I wanted to blend it into the track a
little bit better. So, we're going to go
ahead. We're going to add our reverb. At
this point, you all know the drill.
>> I'm falling [music] apart
and I'm falling in [singing] pieces.
Let's go back to the start.
Baby, give me a reason
to stay.
And then we have like a different
electric guitar that comes in there.
Kind of cool. So, we now have our song.
Let's remind ourselves what we did. We
started with these MIDI chords up here.
And with more time, we could clean some
of the stuff up, be more detail-
oriented. But then we added these
ambient synth parts. We recorded the
vocal. We scratch vocal in the uh like
voice memoy thing. We took all of that,
we covered it. We pulled the drums and
the guitar part out of that indie
version of the song. Um, we layered in
that female vocal and then I recorded
some background vocals and we have our
fingers crossed that at some point we
have some pitch correction that comes
into studio 2. Okay, let's listen to
this.
It must have [music] been a bad moment.
Getting late and still working
and me [music and singing] ignoring all
the warnings. Cautionary stories over my
head.
You must have had a bad [music] feeling.
Saw the cracks [singing] in the ceiling
and me pretending [music]
I don't see. We're just in a season
painted red
and I'm falling apart
[music]
and I'm falling in pieces.
Let's go back to the start. [music]
Baby, give me a reason
to stay. to stay. [music]
>> [music]
>> Okay. Um, that's a demo. I can go bring
that somewhere, show someone this song
that I wrote and kind of show them the
vision that I have from an
instrumentation perspective on it. So,
now that I've done this thing, what do I
do with it? Well, there's a few things I
can do. We have this export button in
the upper right. So, we've got three
options here. We have full song, which
exports this whole thing as one song
into my Sunno library. We've got
selected time range that allows you to
select a specific duration of time that
I want to export. And then multittrack
will render out each track individually
and download it to your computer in a
big zip file. And then one other thing
here is I can also download any of these
clips as a wave file or as MIDI by
right-clicking it. So if I've got
something like this keyboard part, I can
either rightclick downloaded as audio,
download as MIDI, or if I want to like
see and play with the MIDI, I can
actually
drag it onto a MIDI track and it'll tell
me that I can convert it. So we'll go
ahead and see how this MIDI sounds in a
second. But those are all of your
different export options. Finally, I can
come up here. Whoa, that was kind of
quick. Let's actually bring this onto
that same patch we were using before and
hear how this sounds. [music]
[music]
Cool. So, if I'm a producer, I can go
ahead download that MIDI and render it
out on any instrument that I want. Play
with it. That's super useful, I found.
And then the final thing I can do is I
can share this project with someone else
who has studio. So if I go up here to
the upper left and I click on the
project, there's this share project
button. And this allows me to get a link
where someone else can view and copy and
make their own like remix or edit of
this project. So if you're collaborating
with someone, you can send these links
back and forth. Right now these links
aren't realtime links, so you won't see
each other's changes made in real time,
but maybe that will come someday. Thank
you so much for watching. Please drop a
comment below with features you're
excited to see come to Studio. And
there's a link down below with a
playlist of a bunch of different videos
that go into more detail about the
plugins and the other features in Studio
[music] 2. And I'll see you in the next
one.